- [Colin Beavan] We try to live in a city
causing no environmental impact
and I write about NoImpactMan.com.
We're just cutting down too many trees.
We need the trees to save the planet.
And the polar bears.
I'm trying to live a life in line with my values.
[Sighs] Oh fuck!
♪ [music] ♪
*- [TV Host] People are intent
on replacing the American way*
with wind power and tree bark burgers.
[Audience Laughter]
Like this one New York family,
the Beavans, who are five months
into a year long quest to live without
impacting the environment.
*The rules: no toilet paper,
no incandescent bulbs*
*or disposable razors or magazines,
or newspapers,*
*television, planes, trains, automobiles,
elevators, plastic bags*
*or shopping for anything new.*
They're poisoning our capital society,
and here now to defend himself
is the patriarch of this eco-Mansons,
Colin Beavan.
Mr. Beavan, thank you so much for joining.
[Audience Cheering and Applauding]
- Joining us now is the writer and
self-proclaimed No Impact Man, Colin Beavan.
- We begin tonight with one man,
his family and a radical experiment
to help the planet.
*with more than 40% of the public*
*now convinced that humans
are part of global warming.*
*- [Colin] I just thought, what if
I actually tried*
*not to hurt the environment,*
*What would that feel like?*
*Is it possible? Is it practical?*
[plane taking off]
[busy street noise]
- One of the things that I,
as a writer have wanted
because my last two books were
history books
for this to become more like
an activist writer.
In some sort of humble way,
I want to have some sense that
my writing is helping the world.
*For the next year, my wife,
baby daughter and I*
*while living in the middle
of New York City*
*are going to attempt
to live without making*
*any net impact on the environment.*
Ultimately, this means we'll create
no trash or no take-out food,
emit no carbon dioxides,
so no driving or flying;
pour no toxins in the water,
so no laundry detergent;
buy no produce from distant lands,
so no New Zealand fruit.
Not to mention, no elevators, no subway,
no product in packaging, no plastics,
no airconditioning, no TV, no paper.
Blah-blah-blah-blah.
Anyway, so that's kind of like
a summary of the project.
♪ [music] ♪
[busy street noise]
*- [Michelle Conlin] Colin told me what
the project would be*
*and my honest reaction? I was really
excited that he had an idea*
*that he was excited about.*
*That was overall
the most important thing.*
I thought, as long as we're doing
all these things,
why don't we throw in
my two current addictions
which are shopping and reality TV?
I'm a reality TV aficionado,
addict and expert.
- *Look at her face right now.*
[Laughter]
*She's like, aren't you looking like
you'd get sucked in.*
- It's good.
I've had a really intense relationship
with retail.
Catherine Malandrino sample sale.
Jean Paul Gaultier is so fun
and I'll see you at midnight
and then we'll have dinner at 2 am.
Marc Jacobs is like
"I'm married, I'm a mom
but I'm still trying to work it a little bit."
I'm like a high fructose,
corn syrup addicted,
You know, screen addicted,
meat-eating girl.
I would say that I was not
an enviromentalist.
I would say that I was the typical,
like consuming -
I'm a consumer.
I'm a take-out junkie.
- You were scared of not being able
- Alright, not having.
- to consume for a year.
*- Yeah, I was. You're right!*
- So, you've been, you're trying to do
all your year's consuming in one week.
*- So I dropped the paycheck.*
Chloe boots that was a lot.
*- How much?*
- In a way, I'm appalled at myself.
*- Can you say how much, though?*
- That's appalling. That's like,
that's just...
I can't even. I'm embarrased.
[Colin laughs]
This was the, you know,
the last rush.
- Yes, this was the binge. I got you.
- Yeah! That's the bill of the binge.
- I got, I was laughing because I was
just looking for like necessities.
*- That was like Custer's last stand
right there.*
- Okay.
- Spending all my money on silly things.
*- I don't care how much you spend.*
This particular spending has to do with...
- Your project.
- No Impact. I thought it was our project.
- Oh yeah.
It's "No Impact Man."
Its his book and that's his project
and he's "No Impact Man"
but in order- but the project is
our family's doing this.
[train running]
- Two weeks ago,
On day one of the project,
we stopped using carbon producing
transportation,
*which means no airplanes, no subways,
no taxis and no elevators.*
*People say, "Well, why get to extreme?"*
*because not everybody
is gonna get so extreme*
and all this kind of thing is to experience
like the whole gamut of things
to see what we really
are willing to give up, you know.
At the end, we'll come out of it and
see what are we willing to keep.
What are we not, what was too hard,
what wasn't too hard.
*The paradigm is reduce, reuse, recycle.*
*So the first thing is reduce.*
*Reduce our consumption, right?*
*Well, I think to myself, you know,*
*"Of course, I can't do without this.
I can't do without that."*
*So the idea is, okay,
let's do without it all.*
[dogs barking]
- Coming in see the T. V.
How big the T. V is.
- Yeah, come on in.
- Happened?
- They're gonna take the T. V away.
*- Frame out.*
[child whimpers]
*- and we're just gonna not have a TV.*
We're just gonna be TV-less people.
- Yeah.
- Mommy is a little bit addicted to the T. V.
[dog barking]
*- I'm gonna be 40 this summer
and there were just so many things*
about the way that I was living my life,
especially with Isabella
that I wanted to change.
I had my blood tested, like really in depth
and it showed that like if I didn't change
the way that I was eating,
I was like on my way to diabetes,
and had a low thyroid.
And then that kind of co-mingled
with my 40th birthday.
It's kind of like that moment in life
when I think,
"Well, where do I want the second half
of my life to look like?"
Since the first half is done.
Tick tock.
*- [Colin] The project works in phases.*
*I'm not a trained environmentalist
so I'm learning as I go.*
*Right now, we're really working
on our trash.*
*The average American creates
1600 lbs. of trash a year.*
*We're trying to reduce that to zero.*
♪ [music] ♪
See that Hawthorne Valley Farm,
certified organic bio-dynamic.
- Yeah.
- *I'm gonna see if we can all, as a family*
*go stay on that farm for like
a few days and volunteer and stuff.*
*Is that okay?*
- Yeah, babe. That sounds like
a great idea.
[Both laughing]
- The majority of our trash is
food packaging and food waste.
The good thing about
the Farmers Market
is that most of the food
is sold unpackaged
so it's easy to shop there
and not make trash.
- No environmental impact?
- Yeah, causing no
environmental impact.
- Really?
- Yes.
- Then you can't have this bag.
- Thank you!
How do I say this without
sounding like a dick?
*I get upset to see things individually
wrapped in plastic.*
Oh, you know what,
Are the worm people here?
- What do you need the worms for?
I don't know if I'm...
- Well, can I tell you about it after?
Basically, the worms
make a compost faster.
*- Honey, I'm not into that at all.*
- Okay, we can talk about it.
Michelle!
*- Yeah?*
- Wanna come see the worms?
[Isabella giggles]
See them wiggling around in there, Mom?
- Yeah. And then how do you
make sure they don't get out?
- They can't get out.
[child babbling]
- Wait. Is there no cover?
- Of course, there is a cover...
- Let's cover it up.
- Know what, Isabella's looking at them.
*- Okay. Nature.*
[Colin laughs]
Mom doesn't really like nature
but Dad likes nature.
[Colin laughs]
- So diaper.
Diaper cover made from wool,
organic wool nicely treated lambs.
I checked into all this.
There's like five different techniques
and there's like the bikini fold
and the angel fold and so whatever,
we're gonna try the angel fold.
There's confusion over whether
cloth diapers or disposable diapers
are better for the environment.
And the industry-funded studies
suggest that it's the same.
*But the fact of the matter is*
*we put 49 million plastic diapers
a day in the landfills.*
It's the third largest source
of trash in the landfills.
[Isabella talking]
- Does it feel different, honey?
- It's too fun!
- It's too fun.
Let's see.
He-hey!
*- Ohhh!*
- He-hey!
Look at you!
- The Green Century Babe.
- Yahaha.
[Michelle laughing]
[hands clapping]
*- We come here every Sunday
for breakfast and we love it.*
But as a part of our column,
our "No Impact" project,
we're phasing out everything
including restaurants.
So this is our last supper at Pasti's
and our last supper in a restaurant
together as a family, right?
- You know we're gonna eat food
only from within 250 miles
so it's not that Pasti's per se
is a problem but for example,
the wheat and the bread probably comes
from the Great Plains, way far away.
So it's - that's what the problem will be.
That, you know the food comes
from all over the place
and we're trying to eat locally.
We can eat what we have except
for the spices because you know,
the spices would last all year.
Onions are not a problem.
Garlic is not a problem.
Squash is not a problem.
Potatoes are not a problem.
We had bacon potatoes
cooked last week for three days.
- I've gone off, off meat but I still
have been eating fish
so last night started like no meat,
no fish, no nothing.
So, I mean out of everything -
out of the stairs,
the scooter and the no garbage,
I've definitely found the food
to be the hardest.
It's still hard like right now,
I just wanna go get like a baked good.
- Why do you think foods
are the hardest for you?
- Because I can't eat anything
that tastes good.
[Both laughing]
*- We're stuck now with cabbage
and root vegetables*
*until the winter's over
and the spring comes.*
*Hi Ryan!*
I'm gonna come back in a little while
to get some milk.
I've got too much to carry already.
- We'll see ya!
The guy that they usually give
my egg cartons to isn't here.
The transportation of food
creates a lot of carbon emission.
Here in the United States,
the average piece of food
has traveled 1500 miles
from the farm to the plane.
These guys have great apples.
I'm wondering what your favorite is?
- [Male Customer] The Winesap
so I'm now gonna talk to him.
[....00:12:52:07] socks off.
*- But they're also lots
of other reasons for eating local*
*like preserving our farmlands.*
And the reason were vegetarian is
worldwide-meat eating is responsible
for more green house gases than
anything else including transportation.
- There's no locally grown coffee
so I have to cut it out.
So today's my last try with
Iced Colada Espressos.
I am worried that I'm gonna have a slip,
that I'm not gonna be able to do it
and then I'm worried about
the wrath of Colin.
Because it really bothers him
when I have slips
because it makes him feel like
the project is going to pot.
Basically, this is easy for Colin
and this is just like murder for me.
The food and the caffeine.
That's Mommy's third and last
Iced Colada Espresso.
Prepare for take off!
Feeling good!
Oh my God! Much better.
♪ [music] ♪
*- [Colin] Part of eating local is
about getting to know the farmers*
*that you're getting your food from.*
So we're gonna go see Ronnie at
*Ronnie Brook Farm*
and all his little cows.
*This is the first time I've been*
on any sort of non-self propelled
transportation for more than a month.
So it's kind of fun.
Choo-choo!
[Laughs]
♪ [music] ♪
*- [Farmer] Every cow has a name.*
This is Thelma.
*- [Colin] Hi girl.*
Is the relationship with the animals
part of why you do it?
- That's the reason we started them.
My wife tells me that when my
son was born, I had to milk the cows.
I couldn't go to the --
take her to the hospital.
[Colin laughs]
I didn't know, I didn't remember
that one.
[Colin laughs]
- Let's talk about organic.
You don't have the organic label.
Why don't you and what do you think
about the organic label and...
- Well, I think organic is a good thing.
The one thing that I am opposed to
as organic
is not being able to treat your cows.
- Right.
[clears throat]
- That's the only thing that I couldn't
subscribe to.
- Which is what? Explain that to me.
- Well, if the cow gets sick,
you can't use any antibiotics.
That's the problem I have
is letting cows die.
These have been the same cows
for generations.
- Wow!
Hi honey!
So let me ask you this.
So everything you're saying,
so let's go to the other end.
People are like on-board
the organic marketing bus.
- The most important thing,
the reason locals' important
is I want to make the food channel legible.
if I'm gonna buy a grape from you
*I wanna go see what you're doing.*
*You might not be certified organic*
*but everything you do
is organic or better.*
In milk, it only has to be,
It only has to be local
and you have to go see the treatment
of those animals.
You gotta go see it!
[people talking]
[cars passing by]
- [Colin] This is an entirely
local food fritata.
Now the root vegetables come from
an up-state farm.
Red cabbage also up-state New York.
Eggs and cheese
from up-state New York too!
*- [Michelle] Did you hear
the phone ring?*
*- I did.*
- That was Robin.
*- Yeah?*
And basically the deal is that
they wanna try and make
this the cover story.
*- Yeah.*
But early Monday morning,
like at seven am,
Robin needs to have
the new draft in his hand.
So I'm feeling so debilitated by
my caffeine withdrawal
that I feel like it's gonna affect my work.
*- Uh-huh?*
- I feel like this is a really important story.
- So it is what I think, why did you
wait until you tell me
when are you gonna start
doing the work?
- After our dinner party.
*- Why don't you wait till then
and then you can decide.*
[dog barking]
- You gotta be kidding me?
I feel like my head is about
to pop off my body.
[spoon drops]
It's gonna help me through the process
and I feel like it's gonna be stressful
and so why not avail myself of that help?
*- Just a second*
*What you really mean is you want
some coffee right now. *
It's got nothing...
- I'm gonna take the dog out.
You SOB!
*- Oh,that's what you really,
that's what you really...*
- Yeah, I wanna go use.
I wanna go on a run.
- Well, I don't care.
*- But you do care.*
- Well, you know.
- I eat only local food.
I don't create any garbage.
I don't eat anything...
*- Wait. Wait. Wait. Wait. Wait.*
*- Progress!*
- You only eat local food but who provides it,
gets up in the morning
and makes your breakfast everyday.
*- You!*
- Does your lunch.
- Does your dinner.
*- That wasn't the point!*
- Then generally washes the dishes
when it's all done?
*- I wash the dishes!*
- What really happened is
Robin called you up
and you thought "Oh, this is an excuse."
[Isabella whimpering]
- So you're gonna have --
you're mad at me
and I'm telling you that
I'm gonna go take care of myself.
- You're putting words in my mouth.
- Okay. Alright!
- I never said I was that.
- I am now going to take care of myself
and get an iced quad espresso
and maybe two, I don't know.
*I don't want to let everyone down.
I don't want myself down.*
[Chuckling]
- I used this spicy olive oil and it's
the remnants of our olive oil
because pretty soon,
we won't be able to use olive oil.
- [Male Visitor: And you're gonna do
without power here?
*- Eventually.*
*- Yeah!*
- What about power in somebody
else's apartment?
*- [Colin] If somebody were to invite us
to watch TV at their house,*
we'd say yes because it was a
social occasion.
*I'm not begging but close.*
[Laughter]
- [Female Visitor] Used clothing?
- Used clothes are allowed.
- Uh-huh!
- No new materials but Michelle,
I think wants to go cold turkey.
- For the whole year, I'm not
gonna buy anything all year.
It's been really great letting it go
because I've been able to
re-think everything.
What do I use?
What don't I use?
- [Lady Visitor] There's a common
style, anyway.
[Laughter]
With a few special friends.
[music]
- [Lady Visitor] Yay, good job!
*- [Colin] At first because it is was
our habit to watch TV, we missed it.*
And now that space is filled with being
in the moment
with friends and each other.
♪ [music] ♪
- I'm making corn mill porridge
which we have a lot.
You'll notice that I don't make it
that much because you know,
there's not that much we can get locally.
So, corn mill porridge is what it is.
- [Isabella] My apple!
Okay. Give Mommy a kiss goodbye.
- I love you!
I'll see you later, okay honey.
I'm gonna go to work.
♪ [music] ♪
- I put a post on the blog called
*"How we avoid making trash."*
No Indian food and throw away
take-out cut tubs.
No Chinese food and plastic
throw away tubs.
No Italian food and plastic
No soda cans. No water in plastic bottles.
Cancelling our magazine and
newspaper subscriptions.
Putting in ends to the
junk mail tree killing.
I'm calling of the companies to ask
them not to send them to us anymore.
Returning egg and berry cartons to the
vendors at the farmers market for reuse.
Buying milk in returnable,
reuseable bottles.
Carrying my ultra cool reusable
cup and water bottle
which is a glass jar I diverted
from the landfill.
Using baking soda from a recyclable
container to brush my teeth.
Switching to real, meaning cloth diapers.
Shopping for food only from the bulk bins
and from the local farmers market
where is unpackaged and fresh.
If I want what's inside this box,
why do I need the box?
And inside the box, there's a bag.
No throw away plastic razors
and blade cartridges.
Using old cloths for rags around
the apartment instead of paper towels.
Keeping a worm bin to compost
our food scraps and to nourishment,
it can be returned to the earth instead
of toxins that seep from the landfills.
Here they go.
- [Male] They're gonna eat,
I think you told me,
three pounds of food material --
- a week, yeah.
For the products, we took four days
where we saved all our trash
and there was 90 gallon.
Four days, which is kind of disgusting.
*This is our combined trash for a week.*
- Isabella talking phone.
Okay so, we've done the trash phase.
*- Yeah.*
- and we've done the local eating phase.
- and now we're moving into the
sustainable consumption phase.
- What about like transportation
and all the other stuff we've done?
- Yes, but those aren't part of the phases.
[Laughs]
So, now we're moving into --
- Okay.
- You know making sure
that we don't have
any environmental impact
through purchasing basically.
So the first rule is
don't buy new products, okay.
But we can borrow, rent or buy used.
- Do you have to go to the potty?
- Yes!
- You have to go potty?
- No!
- Do you want some toilet paper?
Actually we're out of toilet paper.
Hey, do we have any toilet paper?
*- [Colin] No.*
One thing that's really really hard
is for a consumer to figure out
*what's okay to buy
and what's not okay to buy*
and what should be disposable
and what's not disposable, right?
- Yeah!
- So that research is really, really hard to do
and nobody can do it all.
- Yeah!
- But, if you just cut out consuming
the things you don't really need,
- Yes.
- you've already done it!
- Yes!
- You don't have to do the research.
- You don't.
- So if you discover that really,
you don't need toilet paper
you can just reuse cloths.
- Yeah.
- Yeah. You don't have to buy toilet paper
and you don't have to do the research
about toilet paper.
- No!
- You get it?
- Yeah!
- Do you really wanna be this
graphic because...
[Isabella laughs]
- The thing about it is
you don't know until you try.
- I feel like I'm gonna lose my job.
- Toilet paper, toilet paper..
[Michelle laughs]
- And public health mockery of us,
it's just gonna be...
*- [Colin] It's a one year experiment.*
- Right.
Isn't it making you, *No Impact Man*
so fringed and wacko
that you'll just be discounted
as a fringe wacko?
I'm just asking rhetorically.
- But if I tried it and I found
out that it works
and its enviromentally better
and it's not problem
and it can be done just as hygienically,
then I know don't see why
it would cheapen it.
But, but if I don't try it...
- Okay.
- I won't know it all.
- Uh-huh.
- You see.
[Isabella talks]
- Uh-huh.
What's bad about toilet paper?
*- We need our trees to absorb
carbon dioxide but instead,*
*we're cutting them down
to make toilet paper.*
So part of our experiment is
just to ask
"Do we have to be a disposable
culture?"” Right?
And toilet, but you know --
and its an extreme
because we're looking at every angle
of that disposable-ness
because the throw away culture
itself is really a big problem.
and actually if we were, you know
maybe we can get away
from everything
that we throw away.
- Tonight I was like, okay well,
if you're gonna ask me to do this,
then I should be getting a prize,
a coupon or a voucher
redeemable for something.
but I don't really want anything
and then my next thought was
I felt the sadness for the wanting
part of me
kind of dying a little bit and it felt like
there was just a hole there.
- So what is left?
- What's that?
- It's all the stuff that were gonna give
away from cleaning out the closets.
- Okay you ready?
- This is called inventory reduction.
[Michelle gasping]
I've never ever been here before
where they put up a Marc Jacobs' store.
- You already have that exact same bag.
- No I don't, honey.
Honey, I have the white Sophia.
- And what's that?
- That's not white. It's like kind of taupe
but its a totally different bag.
[car honking]
Maybe ours was a little bigger.
I don't know but anyway,
just reminds me of our T. V.
[chuckles]
- [Radio Host] You're on New York
public radio WNYC FM and AM New York
and WNYC dot org.
Mostly sunny skies
in Central Park at ten o’clock.
My first guest today is *No Impact Man*
Colin Beavan just walked up 24 flights
of stairs, accompanied by your host
who's not proud or tired to avoid
consuming electricity in an elevator..
For those of you who happen to have
the *New York Times* around,
take out section F,
the House and Home Section.
There's a big green, tinted picture
of Colin Beavan's apartment
with his wife, his daughter and everything.
[music playing]
One of the biggest pictures I've ever seen
in the *New York Times.*
[laughs]
One of the littlest apartments
I've ever seen in the *New York Times.*
[laughs]
I rode home from Bryan's show
and I thought
I wonder if any of my friends saw
the *New York Times* story
and e-mailed me to say congratulations
and there's a 150 e-mails.
The subject line says things like
"Greetings from the Today's show."
*Hi. This is Mary Noel.
I'm a producer for Bill Mark.*
At first I was excited, but then when
I saw how many requests there were
and I didn't know what to do, I went
from excited to scared out of my mind.
*Hi Colin. My name is Julie,*
*I work with the Discovery Channel.*
*"Hi Mr. Beavan, my name is Abe Hagras,
and I'm calling from Al Jazeera English*
*based in Washington D.C."*
People contacting me from Australia,
Colombia, Germany, Italy.
- He's doing a story about families
who live in New York
sort of eco-effective and environmental
green families.
- [Female Interviewere] Can you turn
yourself slightly more towards me?
- You see?
Not to mention like Italian television,
Japanese television.
Interview request from
a newspaper in France.
- [Reporter] [speaking in French]
- Before we started this project,
Michelle and I
- [Radio Host] Sorry you were talking
about the philosophy, what's behind— --
- Okay.
- *No Impact Man.*
- I'm kind of, always thinking about
collective action.
What we as a society should do.
You know, the laws that should be changed.
But one of the things, I've always been
weak on as a Liberal
is individual action like,
"Why do I have to wait for Congress
to do something?"
"Why do I have to wait for big business
"Why don't I do something?"
- The Times though makes it sound like
part change the world,
part gimmick for your next book.
Do you cop to that?
- Yeah, I totally cop to that.
You know I am who I am. This is what I do.
But if I can take the energy of who I am
as a person and point that energy
in a direction that, you know,
I'd say this most humbly
but and point that energy in a direction
that can help the world,
then it's better than pointing it
in another direction.
This is what the *New York Times*
reporter says about the project at hand.
"It may seem at best like a scene from an
old fashioned situation comedy,"
"and at worst, an ethically murky exercise
in self-promotion."
So she wrote basically that
the range of possibilities
was that it's bad or it's really bad.
*To a reader, it was really funny.*
*From my point of view, it undermines
the opportunity to cause people to think.*
♪ [music] ♪
But if we called it "The year I lost
20 pounds without going to the gym once"
or "The year we didn't watch TV and we
became much better parents as a result."
Or if we called it "The year we ate
locally and seasonally,
and it ended up reversing my wife's
pre-diabetic condition."
There are actual benefits
to living environmentally.
So this is the reader's opinions, right?
379 comments. Apparently
it's a huge number of comments.
"Sacrifice now or sacrifice later.
I'm already doing a lot
but plan to do a lot more."
And there's this one "I can't wait
to wipe my ass with this book."
This one says "D. T. M. F. A Michelle"
which I'm guessing stands for
"Dump The Mother Fucking Asshole."
Gawkers aside that kind of parodies
and sends things up that are in the media.
"Colin quietly weeps on the toilet,
too moist to move and
too proud too wipe."
[Laughs]
That was great but the comments,
my first impulse was
to rake these people
with oozy fire while screaming
"Is that enough impact for you?"
I started, I doubted myself
for a little a while.
I go, "I think I'm something worthwhile
but maybe I'm not."
Maybe one, it's philosophically wrong.
I've also got emails from some
environmentalists that say,
*you know, "Crazy people like you
give the rest of us a bad name."*
Could I potentially be making
completely the wrong decisions?
Yeah but you have to --
I'm just trying, you know,
I will just try to ask myself, you know,
to do what my conscience,
you know, I try to follow the dictates
of my conscience.
[water running]
- I know that I can't back out now
and I'm not gonna back out on you.
but it's making me not wanna do it.
- I think that its great, you know,
if we've been reading
the blog and stuff like that.
- One person at work has come up
who I really like. She's a friend of mine
but I guess, everywhere she goes
people are talking about it.
Basically how we're
bourgeois faux and crazy
and she spends all her time defending me.
but one guy, he said,
"My wife has instructed me to never ever
shake your hand."
and she went on all night
about the hygiene and...
I understand why people would criticize
if ever. I just don't get why they hate us.
- Babe, that's -- I don't think they hate us.
- Look at that!
- Completely coincidentally,
Colin and I were invited to brunch
by this woman, Carrie because
she's a food writer.
and it turns out at the end of the brunch
that I discover that she comes clean
with the fact that she had
written negatively about us
and had been one of
our haters on the web.
She claims that she's changed
her mind about us.
I don't know.
- [Kerry Trueman] Alright. Let me see
if I can pull this up.
"I have been dreading this moment.
I was afraid you were gonna ask."
[Michelle laughing]
- You're sport.
- Oh God!
"*No Impact Man* is in fact having an impact
but probably not the one he intended.
Once upon a time, virtue was its own reward.
Now, a vow of voluntary simplicity
is just another entrepreneurial enterprise.
The fact that *No Impact Man*'s
ostentatious embrace of all things organic
did not come about in, well, an organic
fashion is what bothers me.
While *No Impact Man* runs around
air drying his ass for posterity,
less flamboyant folks are leading lives
of quiet inspiration."
[exhales loudly]
I questioned his sincerity and his motives.
- Yes.
- And there was *G Willickers* quality
to the post that rubbed me the wrong way.
- Your criticism in the context of the criticism
is very, very, very, very mild
I didn't quite get why people hated us
or why it was such a...
- I have a theory.
- I didn't quite get it.
- Based on my own experience with
this kind of thing, too much is said
but I think that a lot of this
really touches a nerve for people.
Aside from making people feel guilty
and defensive about
their consumer habits.
People are very traumatized
if you suggest
that they should make do
without something.
If they have the notion of...
- The notion of "I need it!"
- Going without, yeah! I need this..
- But I need it.
- or I" don't need it but I want it and
why shouldn't I have it."
This is being a good American.
♪ [music] ♪
*- [Colin] Part of local food is about
connecting with the way the food is grown.*
*So, I talked to the local
community garden and the waiting list*
*for having your own plot is long,
like years and years.*
*But it turns out that there is only
one person in that community garden*
*who grows vegetables.*
*Everybody else grows flowers.*
And he was actually willing to take me on
and to mentor me.
- [Meyer] You're gonna help us
in the garden?
- Yeah!
- You wanna grow things?
- That's my friend, Meyer.
Be careful. That's a rose bush.
That has thorns.
- [Meyer] See that's really pokey.
- [Colin] Sharp things.
- Let's talk about what we
hope to do today.
*- Yeah.*
- This little plot is gonna be parsley.
Just kind of broadcast it
over this rectangle
and cover it to the depth that it says to
and wherever else.
♪ [music] ♪
- Let me tell you what I'm doing, lovey?
We're gonna put some plants in there
so we're breaking up the soils
so that the plants can grow.
*I thought gardening was supposed
to be hard work, Meyer?*
- It is! I did a lot of the most
labor intensive...
*- When you spread the manure?*
- Yeah!
*- Right.*
- When I dug the whole
fucking place up last fall.
- I'm taking these seeds, right,
and I'm gonna put them in the ground.
Meyer, we're going to go spend
four days up at Hawthorne Valley Farm.
- That whole thing is, is that everything
on the farm is recycled.
*- Yes!*
- It's all self-contained.
- Yes!
*- Very good.*
- I called them up and the whole family -
me and Isabella and Michelle,
it's kind of, gonna be our holiday.
*- That's nice!*
- Yeah.
♪ [music] ♪
*- [Michelle] I feel like we should talk
about having another kid.*
*- [Colin] Uh-huh.*
- But I know that you don't want another kid
so I feel like that means we're probably
not gonna have another kid.
- Umm,
*When we had Isabella, I felt like
you really wanted a baby*
and what I wanted from my life
had account, you know.
Like I just couldn't keep that from you,
*and I was willing to take the leap
with you from that*
because I felt like, I thought it's funny
because we have this history
like I was scared to get married, too
and I would say to you,
"Are we doing the right thing?"
and you said "Yes, "
and I trust in the guidance --
I trusted you and for me
it's totally the right thing.
But when I think about
having a second child,
*- Uh-huh.*
Like whose career's that's gonna get,
whose works are gonna get sidelined?
'Cause like your like totally
running high at work.
If we were to have a second child,
are you willing to give up that work?
- I don't have to, that's so --
that's like I don't have to give up
my job to have a second child.
I don't know why you're bringing --
I don't really feel like my work
has anything to do with it, really.
- It does, because the point is like
I wanna know if we were to have
a second child, right?
I don't particularly want a sec --
I don't want a second child, right?
But before we even
begin to consider it-
there is not much flexibility
in our schedules, right?
So what I'm asking you is where
is the flexibility gonna come from?
- It will come from me!
[door closes]
- Okay.
I'll collect all the cleaning products
we have in the house already.
Standard cleaning products
contain all sorts of chemicals
that aren't good for us.
and they're not good for the
environment either
and they end up getting flushed down
or drained and into the water supply.
What were looking at here are a lot
of things that are marketed
as natural and not harming
the environment already
because we've been
on the project for a while now.
They do not allow you
to refill the bottles
and for the purpose of this product,
we don't use disposable products
and people say,
"Well, what about recycling?"
But the fact of the matter is that
plastic recycling is not as good
as it's made out to be.
It's better than nothing
but it's still not perfect.
So, the people call it "down cycling"
rather than recycling
because it goes down in quality
everytime and then becomes toxic.
As we've been running out of stuff,
I've had - we've saved the empty bottles
so we that we can put our homemade
cleaning products in the empty bottles.
All our cleaning products
can be made from these things.
White vinegar, baking soda,
Castile soap and Borax.
[water flowing]
I don't know. How do you tell
if its really clean?
It feels like it's, you know, it feels
the same as when we're using
a regular cleaner.
Hey Poop, you know what
I'm doing right now, right?
I'm getting rid of all the cosmetics.
- My cosmetics?
Well, aren't we supposed to do that?
- Oh, you mean my make up and stuff?
- Well, I thought so but I don't know.
What are you doing about your make up?
- What are you doing, you're just gonna
throw all that stuff out?
- Well, I'm not. I wasn't gonna throw it out.
I was just gonna put it in this box,
till the year is over.
- Okay. Just let me know.
[Colin Laughs]
- I can't just put all this stuff in this box.
Can you help me?
[bottles clattering]
- Honey!
- Yeah?
- Leave that bottle that says "Fresh" on it.
Just, I'll take care of it.
- I already left that for you.
- Here empty.
- I know, I need that.
[Isabella talking]
- Because you know what I wanna do?
I'm gonna make shampoo
and put it in there.
A few days ago, I blogged about the fact
that we were getting rid of the electricity
I asked for suggestions and I gave
a list of all the things
I needed help with and
one of the things was laundry.
Somebody e-mailed me and said that
they used to do their laundry in the bathtub
and they would just walk on it
and that sounded good to me.
[water splashing]
[Isabella talking]
You wanna do it too?
[water splashing]
Now we go backwards.
[Laughs]
Mom!
[Isabella talking]
We're doing the laundry.
- I wanna do it myself.
You wanna do it yourself? But I'm worried
you'll fall over. Don't fall over.
- Is it, what, what are you cleaning
clothes with?
- You know, Cast -- Oh! I told you not to fall.
[Laughs]
I told you not to fall.
- Honey, what is in there?
- Castile soap and Borax.
- What's Borax?
- It's natural. It's all natural laundry stuff.
You wanna get in?
- Yeah.
[Laughs]
*- [Isabella] I'm doing the laundry.*
- You're doing the laundry.
In college, she's gonna be like...
[Michelle laughing]
- [Gasps] Oh, you made the water so cold!
- Well, they've been soaking
for three hours.
- Well, this isn't fun.
- Come on! It's like crushing grapes.
Come on, get it clean, kids.
Uh-oh I think she's in troublesome.
- Troublesome? Why?
She's only looking for trouble.
*- [Isabella] Laundry!*
- [Together] We're all doing a laundry!
♪ [music] ♪
- [TV Host] Some of your friends
think you're insane.
[Colin laughing]
- And I'm trying to imagine
when they come over for supper
at your house for parsnips or whatever
it is you have lying around.
What do your friends say about this?
With no napkins and no toilet paper,
could you do it?
[audience laughs]
- Nobody has to do what I do.
That's not the important thing.
What I'm doing, it brings attention
to the issue but all of us
should just learn to do what we can do.
- You're now, what,
five and a half months in,
next step is to get rid of the electricity
and live by daylight alone,
in New York City?
- Saturday, there's a switch in my
apartment
which is the circuit breaker
for the whole apartment.
We're having a little party for our friends
and we're gonna click the switch off.
So yeah.
- Well, we should let everybody know.
We're gonna be following Colin
throughout this long year.
♪ [music] ♪
*- [Colin] I was gonna get some spinach
but now that the electricity is going off,*
I realize that I can't buy a lot of stuff.
I got to just buy for the next couple of days
because other than that,
everything will just spoil.
♪ [music] ♪
- Tonight we're switching off
the electricity
and I haven't really thought about it
but I actually feel we're moving
into the sixth month
and I'm starting to really get
into the dividends
and the benefits are really starting
to pour in so I'm actually kind of excited.
but I'm sure that, you know,
talk to me in a day
and I might be just miserable.
Let's just talk a little bit about
what it's gonna be like.
- Well, there's gonna be
a transition period.
That's hard, like everything else.
♪ [music] ♪
- Hi.
- Hi Gracie!
- How are you?
- Hi.
- How is it going?
- Good.
- Hi! How are you?
- [Male Visitor] Consumer recycling
material help us help the planet.
Is that all good enough?
[Laughter]
[people chattering]
- [Lady Guest] The disposable cup.
- [Male Guest] Yes.
- Non-recycable cup and then jacket
and then you have two cups in fact
that looks like it.
You've broken every rule.
- Okay.
*- [Michelle] Have you guys seen
our new refrigerator?*
*You want one, don't you?*
*- Female Guest] Yeah.*
- What's the story?
What's its called?
- [Colin] Its called a "Pot on Pot"
It's invented for use in Nigeria
and the idea is that the water evaporates
from the -- the sand in between the
two pots is wet and the water evaporates.
*- [Lady Guest] Okay.*
- and the energy of the evaporation
is taken from the inner pot
which causes it to cool down
and for example, a tomato
which would only last in Nigeria
two days after picking,
*in this thing would last three weeks.*
*- [Michelle] Right.*
*- [Colin] And there's a glass
of water in there right now*
so we're gonna see
if the glass and water...
*- [Lady Guest] I thought there was
part of the refrigeration.*
- The glass of water is in there
because we're gonna see
at the end of the night
if the glass of water is cold.
- [Male Guest] Oh, I thought that's like
the nuclear coal
[Woman laughing]
that drove the whole thing --
nuclear energy.
*- [Lady Guest] It's not, okay.*
[people talking]
- [Colin] Yeah.
- and are these from
the farmers market?
- Yes!
Okay, here we go!
[switches clicking]
♪ [music] ♪
[glass clattering]
- Its cooler but its not yet cold.
That's where i suppose you can see
if there's a way to make it a bit colder.
- This has become like my
Four Seasons
I have like my lights, I have like -
somebody comes in
like empties my garbage
and there is you know,
plenty of heat and electricity
and air conditioning.
So my huge treat has become
the ice, I'm gonna go show you.
Technically, the ice shouldn't
be allowed either
but I allow myself the ice.
[ice crunching]
It's really good. Its tap -
New York City taps
so it's - this is good as bottled water.
Probably cleaner and better
than a lot of bottled waters.
It's good to get the ice, get really cold
you have to wait for a little bit.
You guys, I wanna run a story by you.
Basically, I got like a really good,
juicy inside dope today.
Its kind of like a what went wrong story.
They focused on their weaknesses.
They totally neglected and
under invested in their strengths.
At this point, I just have to, like,
just report the thing to death, right?
And then see what we have
mid-day Monday.
- [Male] This is a very big story.
- I know I'm thinking the same.
This is the first story where
I didn't even think about
having to do without caffeine.
I'm making some progress.
[cars passing by]
Honey?
Do you remember where
you put the matches?
Hang on, hang on. Here they are.
[Colin laughing]
I got them.
[match striking]
♪ [music] ♪
Its kind of really our first night
without the electricity
because last night we had people over
and we had the electricity
for most of the night.
♪ [music] ♪
Are you down?
Are you mad at me?
- [Colin] No.
- What is it babe?
- It's stupid.
- What? The project is stupid?
- Well, the going without electricity
like, who's gonna go
without electricity?
That's dumb.
- So that's whats really bothering you
or are you afraid that...?
- I didn't think like it's gonna be,
but I feel like this pain in the ass.
[Michelle laughing]
- Can't argue with you there.
- I don't know. I just feel like
the whole project
I mean, made me a curiosity but not...
Everybody will have moved on
by the time the book comes out
and It's just going to be
another irrelevant book.
- Let's just say it turns out
that its totally stupid, right?
Okay, I don't think that.
But like, just worst case scenario.
So, we had, like, a ball.
We've had a ball doing it so far.
I mean it's been hard
but it's been fun, hasn't it?
- Yeah, its been fun.
♪ [music] ♪
*- [Radio Host] New York Public Radio
WNYC FM and AM New York*
*and WNYC dot org*
♪ [music] ♪
*and the heat index issue
is not just a warning.*
*I mean, here it's already 84 degrees
and it's only 50 minutes after ten o'clock.*
[paper slamming]
- It's gross.
- I got home yesterday and there were
flies all over the apartment.
[swatting flies]
There was a bunch of flies
reproducing in my worm bin
and everytime I opened the worm bin,
more baby flies flew out.
[swatting flies]
Oh my God! Look at 'em!
Oh my God!
♪[music]♪
By the way, look at this.
It's like all earth. See?
[birds chirping]
- I didn't think that it would work.
It just doesn't work. Okay.
There's a reason why people
have refrigerators.
The truth is I'm just mad because
I'm like, I'm just devastated about that
little information about getting pregnant.
Look, statistics are so low
and I'm basically turning 40.
And like, note the gray hair
and I just feel devastated about it.
And I feel like it says that somebody
like me would have a 5% chance
like in any given...
It's probably - it's gonna work out your way
anyway because the chances are so low.
- I mean, I totally,
I totally hear that you're sad
and I totally understand
but it feels like a reality show for me
discussing this issue on camera.
- I thought that you want to know
how I felt about the Pot in a Pot.
- Oh, well, that's - I totally wanna know
how you feel about the Pot in a Pot.
- This is how I feel about it.
You know, our whole thing was that
we were gonna like totally support
who the other person
wanted to become, right?
We were gonna kinda be on board
for each other's dreams.
You know, this is important to you
that we don't have a fridge, right?
I'm on board with that.
And then I feel really bummed
because we're like putting
all these energy on your dream, right?
And then, you know, I'm like...
- I mean, I'm totally willing
to work with you
and talk to you about the
prospect of having another child
and, you know, see where
we get to in talking
but if you're connecting it to the project,
I — you know...
- But, this is tied together for me,
they're totally connected.
So, if they're not connected for you, then...
- If I've got this right, you feel as though
you support me but I don't support you.
Like I don't support your dreams.
- I feel like this is my biggest,
most important, like most precious thing.
- Right.
- And I feel like, yeah,
you don't wanna do it
so it's kind of like no.
The answer's no.
- Oh, I want to want what you want.
But, I don't feel like it would be
good for our family
for me to just say,
"Okay, you want it so I'll do it,"
when I have such
strong feelings about it.
- Do you wanna move this out then?
- It's okay honey, we're just gonna
leave that there, just for now, okay?
- Okay.
The Pot in a Pot has been moved out
and this is our latest refrigerator.
To keep it cold,
I mooch ice off of my neighbor, Hillary.
[scooping ice]
- Do you need to come and get it
everyday or how do you wanna...?
- I think this will last a little while in the cooler.
- Ah, yeah. I hope so. I think so.
- Can I carry the bag?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
You can carry the bag.
Let's put the freezer...
Thank you so much.
- You're welcome.
- Say thank you to Hillary, honey.
- Bye. You're welcome.
Bye, Sweetie.
- Okay. Perfect.
*We're gonna take the ice pack
and put it right on top*
*so that your milk stays nice and cold.*
And you wanna just drop
the cubes on there?
Drop them, one by one.
- One by one.
Whoa!
- The refrigerator is my bottom.
The pot in a pot and now the...
I don't know what I hate more
the pot in a pot or this, I'm not sure.
Just mooching power on ice cube,
so I kinda don't get it.
I'm kinda like...
Say, "Bye wacko fridge."
- Bye. Wacko fridge.
- Who cheats more, you or Collin?
- I'm sure I have to cheat more, like this.
*I tried vegetable diet at home
but it was a disaster.*
- Right.
*- He doesn't really cheat.*
*He'll bend the rules a little bit.
That to him wouldn't be a cheat.*
Like, there's no trips this year
because we can't go anywhere.
So, he decides that we're gonna
make an exception
and we're gonna go up to the farm
where they grow our food.
We walked to the station
with our luggage,
this is when the slip started.
I go to Dunkin' Donuts,
there's a huge line
I give the lady this huge tip,
and I'm like, "Could you refill
this glass twice?"
*I get two huge decafs and I'm not
going back at Dunkin' Donuts.*
- Hooking you up.
*- And there's like
ten people behind me*
*but I gave her such a big tip
that she was like,*
*just my girl for a while.*
But, I was like, I don't wanna be
putting our energy into the pot in a pot.
I wanna be having another kid.
I don't wanna spend
my vacation on a farm.
♪[music]♪
When we got married,
I was like, look Colin, I'll marry you
but there is one thing -
I don't like camping.
I'm never going camping with you.
But, now our whole house
has turned into a camp ground.
And also, I don't really like nature.
And now for our vacation,
we're going into nature.
[Laughs]
We're gonna see and work
with all the food that we eat.
For the farmer's market,
this is the farm where it comes from.
♪[music]♪
- Hi, cow.
- You could put your hand out
and touch him.
- Hi, cow.
- Thank you so much for having us.
Thank you.
- [Rachel Schneider] Welcome!
I'm having the best session already,
We've only been here for an hour.
- Yeah.
*- [Rachel] As you work
to steward this land,*
you are growing a very vital,
dynamic being that's in balance.
*It's a closed loop system.*
The cows eat the grass.
They give you milk but they also
give you manure.
The manure is composted.
It becomes the fertility.
*We make about 400 tons
of compost per year.*
And smell it.
- Yeah. It just smells like earth.
It smell just like my worm bin, actually.
- You say though a lot that this kind
of is the realization of his values?
*- Yeah.*
- Do you - how do you feel about it now
six months into that, do you still...?
- I feel like there's no going back.
- There's no going back, right?
Right.
- This is for our family.
It's not just about the project.
- [Male] Where are you from?
- [Colin] I live in the city. I hope to be
more of a help than a hindrance.
[Laughing]
*- [Male Farmer] Let's go.*
[bells clanging]
- [Male] That's Henry. That's the bull.
Come on Henry, let's go.
Let's go to escort Henry
into the barn.
[Cow mooing]
*- [Michelle] The night before we left,*
*the farmer and Colin
were having a conversation.*
*They're talking about how valley
once was populated with sheep.*
*They were also talking about
how people could devolve*
*into like animals.*
*I just felt so transported
by this conversation.*
*And then I went to bed that night
with the beautiful farm air*
*in the beautiful farm house
with these beautiful people*
who treated us like we're family
and I dreamt that
I was one of the sheep.
*It's weird 'cause my grandparents
were farmers*
like they were homesteaders
and I started feeling like —
I feel like my family like
left something back there.
And I was like, I feel like
I'm going back to get it.
*When I listened to the farmer
talking about the herd*
and how sometimes something
will happen to one of the cattle
but that the herd goes on
*I felt like I woke up.*
*I felt like I got to reconnect
with something.*
[horn blowing]
♪[music]♪
A company loaned me this
solar panel for the project.
I can change the way that
electricity is delivered to my house.
- Get it.
- Yeah.
The solar panel will provide
just enough electricity
*so that I can power my computer
and write my blog.*
But, what's really interesting
about this phase is that
*it's the first time that I've realized
that it's not about using as little*
*as we can possibly use*
but finding a way to get
what I need in a sustainable way.
And that's what we need to do with,
you know, with my electricity,
with the solar panel.
But, that's also what we need
to do with our systems.
*We just need to figure out
how to get people what they need*
in a way that doesn't harm the planet.
[typing]
Tell that guy to get out of the bike lane.
Do you wanna know
what I gave her for her 40th birthday?
No birth control.
You know what I'm saying?
We call it Russian Roulette.
- So, now the question is,
is it click-click or bang-bang?
- If it's bang-bang, I die, she lives.
Watch out on your right for a lunatic.
My blog post today was about
opportunities in a crisis.
Imagine if we made the city
nicer to live in.
So, the two comments
on the post so far are
let's be realistic.
Like, you can't make a city nice
so forget it.
There's such a lack of idealism, but
I think realism got us to where we are,
you know what I'm saying?
[horn honking]
- That helps.
You okay Michelle?
- Watch out honey.
- I know. I know.
- It's so quiet.
- I know.
- Oh, that Fort Tilden over there?
- Yeah.
- Oh, my God! This is like the Hamptons.
- It's better than the Hamptons.
- 'Cause there's no one here.
[Colin laughing]
- Oh, my God. How radical is this?
And this is still New York City.
We're in New York City.
- Ooh, bug.
- Will you go swimming with me?
- Well, um...
[waves crashing]
- To me it's amazing
how resilient nature is
like there's sandpipers on this beach
and everybody is trying to survive.
And there's these ant crabs
and they're in New York City.
See the two of them?
- Yup, I see it.
- Wait, wait, wait.
- Ahuh yup, I see.
[waves crashing]
- People can keep talking about,
what's the hardest thing?
Are you depriving yourself?
As though like all these aspects
of the project are hard.
But, it's not about deprivation.
It's not about not taking care of yourself.
It's the opposite.
It's about seeing,
is it possible to have a good life
without wasting so much?
♪[music]♪
- Colin met this amazing woman
at the farmers market, who loaned us her tricycle.
We can roll. It totally changed our life.
We have no TV, no lights,
no electricity, no air-conditioning.
These were all the things that kept us inside.
We're kinda forced out
of the apartment all the time now.
[water splashing]
The days feel like they just last forever.
- What are those?
- They're fireflies.
*- [Isabella] There's a light.*
[Isabella Shrieking]
-Oh, oh, oh, oh!
[Colin laughing]
- Are you playing Gin Rummy?
- Uh-hm, we're playing Gin Rummy.
- I wanna show you something, okay?
This is what you call
kicking dad's ass, okay?
- [Meyer] We're coming from
vastly different spaces.
No one is ever gonna be as naive,
naively hopeful and naively optimistic
as we were in the late '60s.
- But, I think there maybe something
kind of similar
more muted that's happening now.
Not in the same way at all
but I feel like there's a certain quiet
beginning of a rebellion happening.
♪ [music] ♪
- [Meyer] The other thing you need
to point out is this on the ...
This called the Scape. S-C-A-P-E.
I would suggest
you take home one or two of those.
- Okay.
- These are the beans.
You can see how they're grabbing the pole.
And you see this?
- Yeah.
- It's starting to make tomatoes.
- Are you overall optimistic about
human kind or skeptical?
- I'm of the belief that it's always 50-50.
- Right.
- That in fact, you know,
somethings are getting better,
somethings are getting worse.
- Yeah.
- You know, though all these...
every time you try to do something right
no matter what level you're on,
there are, you know, unforeseen results.
My hesitation about your work is that
it enables people to fool themselves
that all they have to do is change
the light bulb
and recycle their plastic bag.
Well, as long as they feel that way,
no politician will pick it up.
- And I feel that it's completely true,
that that's — it's both.
I mean, you need to have...
I think — I think that there's ...
if you have a political stance and
then there's a tremendous integrity
to living in a way that reflects that
political stance.
- At the risk of being too personal,
*- Right.*
- but, you know, it's not,
it's just the facts.
Michelle writes for Businessweek.
*- Yes.*
- Millions of trees are cut down
on a regular basis
in order to promote
the totally fallacious propaganda
that American Corporate Capitalism
is good for the people.
Good for you and me, you know.
Now, if it's your contention that
she makes up for that
that evens out because she doesn't
take the elevator in your 5th Avenue Coop,
I have to say you're either
dishonest or delusional.
- I mean, that there's definitely an irony
if it were in a paradise involved in that, but...
- I mean, who?
Where did all these crap come from?
American Corporate Capitalism
did all of it, you know.
If anybody really thought that
that you were gonna have an impact there,
you wouldn't be getting
the attention you're getting.
♪ [music] ♪
[people cheering and clapping]
- [TV Host] And here's our
No Impact Man, Colin Beavan
in the no impact SUV.
- You may be on my show but I'm not
here to spread your particular gospel
because I think what you're doing
is extremely dangerous, okay?
[Colin laughing]
[camera clicking]
- Oops, there we go. That's good.
Okay, now I've got you like ...
it up so I can see you.
- [Myriam Weil] can see a little bit.
- A little bit.
*- [Myriam] A little bit.*
- Okay, I'm gonna hold something
up for you to see more.
*- [Myriam] It's disgusting.*
- No, it's not.
*- [Myriam] It's something shit...*
- Yeah. It is shit. It's worm shit.
[water dripping]
- I think that my only connection to food
before the project was eating it.
I really ate all my food pretty much
at restaurants or at a take out container.
I never cooked it. I never prepared it.
I never thought about it.
I never composted it.
I never thought about the waste.
Now, that I go to the farmer's market,
I know all the people who grow our food
and kinda have this like little desire
to take it to the next level.
- I'm seeing today as just like
the first session.
- [FemaleCook] Basic, okay. So...
- Like the first lesson.
- So, we're gonna just like make some--
alright, so I've been thinking of
a few things we'd make.
Alright, we'll start, you know,
with the green beans
just snap off just this end.
- Okay, so snap off the kind of
uglier end. This end.
- Exactly.
See, here are the dandelion greens,
I'm gonna just snip the ends off.
So, I'm trying to cut off the end.
- Okay.
- Great.
*- [Colin] Nicely done.*
[Colin laughing]
- You just pre-heat it to 375.
- Yeah.
- [Female Cook] I mean honestly,
I might turn it up a little towards the end.
- I'm gonna make this coffee
but I know you don't want any, right?
- [Michelle] Oh, yeah. I'll have a little.
- Are you sure?
- Yeah. I can have just a little bit.
There's a reason why
I can only have a little bit.
I wonder if you guys
can guess the reason?
I'll just have a little bit of coffee.
- Are you pregnant?
- Oh, my God! You are?
- Yes!
[shrieking]
*- [isabella] Can I go out?*
- Dad's gonna take you out, love.
Dad's gonna take you out.
I'm just gonna put them on, tomatoes.
I'm making dinner tonight and I've
actually never made dinner for us.
- Do you want me to show you
how to get that oven
to get to 350 or 375, it's all tricky.
- Why don't you just
do the oven to 350, 375.
- Okay.
- Yup. Yup. Okay. That's a good trick.
- Okay. And then if you wanna be sure
there's a thermometer down there.
- Oh, that's nice.
- It tells you what the
temperature of the oven is.
- We really love our eggplant.
- It might not workout
but we have to learn and grow.
Tonight I'm just focused on I'm trying
to learn how to roast a vegetable.
- Bye.
- I feel a little performance anxiety.
- I don't know if I should cut this off or...
I feel really nauseous.
[water splashing]
[dog barking]
Shhh.
You know, my whole life I've been like
looking for like gurus
or this program or that thing or --
You know, I've always been kind of
looking for something
and I feel like we're looking
for that thing together
and we're kinda like finding some of it.
I have to admit that like there are times
when I'm just like this asshole.
I had a lot of moments.
Now, I think what he's doing is so cool.
I get like a big kick out of him.
I just think he's like...
hmm, not quite done yet.
Wooh.
Ah, Madam and Monsieur
[foreign language]
[child babbling]
[cars passing]
- You have the idea that you can
park other things besides cars?
- The idea is, why are we dedicating
this land to cars instead of people?
Could you imagine like, if this is
extended all the way up
to 7th Avenue?
*We started a positive impact
phase of the project.*
*The idea is no net
environmental impact*
*so that's reduce our negative impact
and increase our positive impact.*
*And it's not meant to be scientific.*
It's just meant to be philosophical.
Can I live on this planet doing
more good than harm?
*I've been helping with a research
project to do with putting oysters back*
in the Hudson River
which will filter the water.
I went cleaning out tree pits in the Bronx.
I was like, what a crack of shit.
No, impact man this is a project.
There is this network of people who
have been working on this stuff forever.
- [Majora Carter] Once you no longer
live in the ignorance that
when you throw something away
that it actually goes away,
you know, it's just really difficult thing
because yes, your piece of trash
comes to a community like this
where it's processed.
*Most people, as they consume,
don't understand*
*what the real cost of those goods are.*
*The pollution it was created,
you know, to make it.*
*The health effects
that are associated with it.*
We are the point sources for all
the green house gases that everybody
is trying to curb right now.
*I think we should be spending more time*
*recognizing that people's lives
are being compromised every single day*
*and have been for decades.*
[truck passing]
- Twelve thousand trucks a day
go through that neighborhood.
*The diesel particulates in the air
are causing asthma in kids,*
*causing brain damage in kids.*
You know, when I started this project,
I just thought I was just gonna like
make less garbage, not travel so much
and wouldn't I be a hero, sort of thing.
You know, I guess I wasn't so clear
how many issues it was gonna open up.
I'm not talking about the Polar Bears.
I'm not talking about
the people in far away island,
communities who are gonna be hurt
when the ocean levels rise.
I'm talking about people
who already are living
with the effects of our
over consumptive society.
♪[music]♪
- If you would ask me, you know,
nine months ago,
would I ever have my baby be on a bike?
And I would say no.
Absolutely not, that's insane.
And I remember going off on the bike messengers
"Those fucking bike messengers
are fucking insane."
And anybody who would ride a bike
in New York is fucking insane.
and they're making it really unsafe,
the bikers, for us car people,
like SUV renters.
They're making it
really fucking unsafe for us.
And that's like my world view.
[car honking]
And now my world view
has completely slipped on it's head.
The streets have totally been taken over
and they're not for people.
*And then the rapacious consumption
for consumption's sake.*
*And the coma that that induces.*
I'm just re-thinking everything
in terms of what's important.
- Do you feel that, moving forward,
that you feel like there's some other way
of considering your decision?
- Yeah. I mean, you know...
What am I doing to do, just say,
well, I don't care?
♪ [music] ♪
- I'm fixing it so that we get the most
sun that we can.
A big question at the center of the
*No Impact* experiment was whether
one person can make a difference.
One of the things that I
really get worried about
when people talk about the fact that
individual action is not important is that
the thing about individual action
is that it causes people to be engaged.
Our society is not setup to live sustainably.
We need more mass transit,
higher efficiency vehicles,
no more coal burning power plants.
These are hard changes.
The international panel on climate change
said that we need an 80% cut
on carbon emissions by 2015.
That's huge.
As your constituent, the first thing
that I wanted to do is
I wanted to thank you for sponsoring
the energy bill.
- You're welcome.
- Because that gives us a good...
- Gives a whole deal.
- Using less is a start but it's not enough.
We need to demand that
our systems become sustainable.
- You can rock it. I will rock you, okay?
Okay, do you wanna rock
while you look at Frankie?
- We told Isabela, we thought
Michelle had a baby in her tummy
but we were wrong.
She didn't, actually.
- The second--
I guess it was the second time
I went to the doctor.
The first time we went to the doctor,
he was fine.
And then the second time
we went to the doctor
there was not heartbeat.
- Yeah.
There wasn't one.
There was no heartbeat.
- Where are you going?
From the perspective of the story,
it would have been like
the perfect ender of the story.
Like you know, I finally kind of
crossed over
into *No Impact* and really embrace it
and that's what Colin really wanted
and then I got pregnant,
that's what I would have really wanted
and then the project winds down.
It's all kind of in this really great bow.
And it's not a bow, it's a big loose end.
So, it's a loose end.
It's a narrative loose end
and a spiritual loose end.
Just a loose end.
A lot of loose ends in life.
- I think we'll probably try again.
- They're like rainbows.
- Is that like rainbows on your feet?
- [Isabella] Rainbow feet.
- [Meyer] The official swan song
in the garden is when
you turn the soil over in the fall.
That's, that's the official
end of the season.
- It's kind of interesting
because we're coming back
to the food that we were eating
when the project started,
which is like squash, root vegetables,
and stuff like that.
And similarly, the garden
is getting turned.
So, you actually-- you kind of
it's not like you turn the calendar page
and you can tell that a year has passed.
You feel that a year has passed
because you're recognizing
something about the earth.
We're so disconnected,
I think, in the city
from the natural rhythms.
I mean, I didn't know this before
but it's actually a great pleasure
to be connected.
♪[music]♪
- It's freezing in here.
It's November 7th
and we're almost done and I'm cold.
So, a lot of times what I do is I --
say I just got home from work,
I'm wearing a suit
but I come in here
and I get in the covers.
I spend a lot of time
under the covers when it's cold.
We don't talk about it ending.
And it's kind of funny because
we're gonna be separated
when it ends
Because when it ends, for me,
I'm getting on a plane to go
see my parents,
who I haven't seen in a year.
And Colin will be here
and I'm taking Isabella.
So, we-- it's funny we haven't
really talked about it.
But, everybody on the outside
ask me about it.
*- Mom?*
*- What's up Sugar Pop?*
- There no any light in here. I can't see.
- I'm looking forward to reading
in bed with Isabella
with ample illumination,
ample illumination.
You're not tired, are you?
- No.
- You know, next week,
there's a school thing happening in NYU.
Something like 200 NYU students are
gonna try and live *No Impact* for a week.
- I think that's so cool.
- Yeah.
So, like on Sunday I go and we just have
kind of a workshop about how to do it.
And then the following Monday,
I go and I give a big talk.
♪[music]♪
Room 206.
And this week as you experiment,
I think you're gonna see that it's not so bad.
My experiment only lasts two more weeks.
As I come out of the extremes,
some of the stuff that we've given up
we'll take back
but the fact is that the balance
will be that we're just
gonna be substantially
causing less environmental impact
and without adversely
affecting our happiness.
The fact of the matter is that
if only I change
it's not gonna make a difference.
But, the hope is that if each of us
as individuals change,
it's going to inspire everybody to change.
So, I believe the most radical,
political act there is, is to be an optimist.
The most radical, political act there is,
is to believe that if I change,
other people will follow suit.
The reason why I am here is
because a first grader called Olive,
wrote to me on my blog
and asked me if I would come.
People ask me, if I could just
do one thing, what should it be?
Not use plastic bags
or not use plastic cups,
I would say, if there was
only one thing to do
it would be to volunteer with
an environmental organization.
Part of the reason for that
is because there is community.
I believe very strongly that a lot of the
environmental problems in our planet
have come because of the
breakdown of community.
Because without community,
none of us feel accountable
to anybody else.
All of us are interconnected
and on many levels.
You know, if you're religious
then you understand
that at a religious level.
But even if you're just practical,
you can see
that we're interconnected,
you know.
If I, you know, splash a puddle
and you're standing next to it,
it splashes you.
If I, you know, make pollution
you have to breathe it in.
My mind wants to tell me
that I'm the only one that's important,
you know,
so I have to keep teaching myself
over and over again that that's not true.
*- [Lady Guest] And then when you turn
the light on, are all the lights gonna go on?*
- Most of them. I try to ...
*- Okay, just as soon as you do that
they're all gonna go on.*
- No, no, no.
Because I have to do it just a few flicks.
Because there's more than
one circuit breaker.
- Alright, so you have to do like three
like hit three circuit breaker
and then they all will be on.
- Yes.
- So, we should light this ... okay.
- Okay.
- It's been-- well, it hasn't really been a year
because the electricity phase
started like around month six.
So, it's been six months
since we've had electricity.
So, it's gratitude for small pleasures.
- Ohhh.
- Yey!
[child babbling]
[blowing sound]
- Here we go.
♪[music]♪
- I have to say I was really skeptical
about a lot of things in the beginning
and I thought they were insane
*and really stupid and I hated and
resented you, alternatively, for them.*
But, I really, really wanna keep the biking.
I wanna keep as much
as we possibly can the no garbage.
And I really, really wanna keep
the farmer's market.
♪[music]♪
I wanna be a vegetarian
but I wanna have a hotdog, now and then.
[Colin chuckling]
I would be a vege-hoggian or vege-dogian.
♪[music]♪
I'd like to not have TV in the house
but I can't wait to go to the movies
and when we're on vacation,
that thing is on.
There are some things
I have some issues with.
- Yeah.
- Why can't we take those worms back?
Because they do make
Lord of the Fleece in the kitchen.
And also there are some things that
we'll just not gonna be able to do
maybe and that might be one of them.
'Cause I get to make
some decisions around here.
♪[music]♪